Now that we've seen how we can get started using selenium webdriver to automate
our browser, the next step is to figure out how to use selenium
to find and locate specific HTML elements on the webpage.
Just between where we quit our driver and where we get hold of a particular
page,
I'm going to show you how easy it is to complete the previous task in day 47
where we try to get hold of the price of a particular item on amazon.com.
This was the item that we were interested in. This was the instant pot
and this is the price.
So if I go ahead and take this URL and replace this previous
just amazon.com URL with the URL that takes us to this page,
then, we can start inspecting on this particular element.
So here we've got the price,
which is that inside a span with the id of priceblock_ourprice.
Now, if I use that,
then I can simply say driver.find_element_by_id
and then I can paste in the id that I found just now,
and this is going to be equal to the price element. Now,
if I want to get hold of the price,
all I have to do is to print that element.text.
And now if I hit run,
you'll see our browser open up briefly to the page with the Instant pot
and then it'll close down and you can see the price printed right here.
Now,
the reason why this is so much shorter than what you did in the last project is
because we're driving a browser.
So the browser is already sending all of those headers,
all of the information that Amazon would expect from a actual user instead of
using a get request using the request package.
So in only three lines,
we can do so much more than we could do with Beautiful Soup. Essentially,
if you think about it,
Beautiful Soup is really good for just grabbing and scraping pieces of data
from an HTML website.
But it gets stuck when that website is being rendered
using JavaScript or Angular or React
and the content that was HTML was taking time to load,
or it requires certain conditions to load.
Whereas in this case,
we're effectively doing exactly the same thing as we would as a human,
going to this particular URL,
and then looking at this element and its value.
I wanted to show you a couple of other ways that you could find elements because
as soon as I write driver.
find, you can see there's a whole bunch of ways of finding elements
and there's a lot more methods than you have with Beautiful Soup.
One that I want to show you that's quite useful is find_
_element_by_name. If we go to python.org,
you'll remember from your lessons on HTML and CSS that most forms,
these input forms, will have a name attribute.
So if I go ahead and inspect on this search bar, you can see its got an ID,
it's got a name, it's got a type, it's got a role, it's got a class.
It has got a whole bunch of attributes.
Now I'm going to search for it by this name, which is q.
And I can do that by saying
find_element_by_name and then specify the name as q.
Now of course I'll have to change this URL to actually python.org.
And now once we've found our element by name,
we'll call it the search_bar,
...
and then we'll go ahead and print out this search bar.
Right.
When selenium locates a particular element,
it won't actually print out the actual HTML.
It'll give it to you as a selenium element like this. Now,
if you want to tap into its various attributes or text or tag name,
then you'll actually have to do that using a dot.
So we can say search_bar.tag_name,
and it will give us that that is an input tag.
Or we could say search_bar.get_attribute
and we can specify the attribute that we want the value for. So for example,
if I wanted to know what the placeholder value was,
then all I have to do is put, get attribute placeholder,
and then we can print that out.
And it will tell us that placeholder says search.
So that is something that you'll find people commonly use with Selenium, find
element by name.
And it's really useful when it comes to filling in web forms because most forms
will have elements that are organized by name because when the form is
submitted,
that name is carried along with the value of the inputs.
In addition to find element by name, you'll also see the usual ones.
So find element by class name, for example.
So if we wanted to get hold of this logo here,
then it has a class of python-logo.
So all I have to add here is the name of the class
which is python-logo
and this will give me that logo element. Now from the logo element,
I can actually get hold of things even like it's size.
So let's go ahead and print out the size of the logo.
Right.
It has a height of 82 and a width of 290.
So you can see that we can do a lot more with selenium than we could with
beautiful soup.
So that's fine element by ID, by name, by class name,
but there's also of course find element by CSS selector.
And this is probably one of the easiest ways of narrowing down on a particular
element.
Let's say that I wanted to get hold of this link to the docs.
Let's go ahead and inspect it, and it lives inside an anchor tag.
But you can see that this anchor tag has no class,
it has no ID, has no easy way of identification.
So how do we get hold of it? Well,
we can see that it lives in a paragraph element and then going further up,
it's inside a div with this particular class.
So this has a class of documentation-widget.
So that's pretty specific. So if we wanted to get hold of that anchor tag,
we could just say, well, inside this div of documentation-widget,
let's go ahead and find any anchor tags.
And to express that as a CSS selector,
we would specify the class documentation-widget,
and then inside the element with that class, we're looking for an anchor tag.
So this would get us our documentation link.
And now if I go ahead and print the documentation_link.text,
you can see that it's actually getting hold of this particular link.
And this is done
even though the actual link doesn't have any easily identifiable name or class
or ID. Now on a similar vein
sometimes it's extremely hard to even find an element even by CSS selector.
So if all else fails, one that will always work as the XPath.
The XPath is a way of locating a specific HTML element by a path structure.
So you've seen what paths look like right?
Users/angela/Development, et cetera. Well,
we can also express the navigation to a particular element drilling down from
the top of the tree to a particular node using the XPath.
Let's say I wanted to get hold of this link at the bottom, submit website bug.
Let's go ahead and inspect on it.
And you can see it's not particularly unique in terms of having an ID or a class
or a name. And even in terms of its structure,
it's sort of in this ul and then an li and it might not be that easy to get
to it. But here's where our XPath comes in handy.
Let's go ahead and right click on it and then go to copy, copy XPath.
And now we can go back to our code and use it to tap into that element.
So we'll say driver, and then we'll say, find_element_by_xpath.
And then inside here, we're going to paste our XPath.
Now notice that the XPath itself actually has some double quotes.
So we have the change
our double quotes into a single quotes so that it doesn't clash with the
inner double quotes. So like this.
Now once we found our bug link,
then we're going to print out the link and I'm going to get hold of the href
here.
So now I'm going to print my bug_link.txt just to prove that this worked.
And if I hit run,
you can see it opens up our browser and you can see it's managed to get hold of
that particular link using this very specific XPath
which looks very much like a file path that we've been using.
But it's essentially the way that we would navigate down through the divs,
the uls, the lis,
all the way down to that particular anchor tag. And the best part of all is of
course,
you can use this button here in Chrome to locate any element.
And then that would select its location in the code
and then you can right-click and then copy it XPath to get hold of that
particular thing.
Now I'm going to link to the documentation on XPath from w3schools.
It goes into a little bit more detail about how XPaths are constructed,
but you don't need to know this in order to work with them. As I've shown,
you can simply use the Chrome developer tools and it will help you get to the
particular item you're interested in.
Now we've been looking at finding elements using selenium,
but notice how we've always stuck to the singular version of that method,
find element. Now for every single method that I've shown you,
there's also a counterpart, which is the find elements.
So, for example, find_elements_by_css_selector. And of course,
this is just going to find you everything on the screen that matches your
criteria and give it to you in a list.
And there is a version of this for every single find method that we've shown
so far. In the next lesson
I've got a quick challenge for you to put into practice what you've learned and
to be able to locate any given elements on a webpage. So
for all of that and more I'll see you on the next lesson.